Guide to the George Baehr Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
George Baehr papers
1915-1978
MS 841
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
5.5
(13 boxes)
Correspondence, writings, scrapbooks, photographs and subject files. While the papers do not fully document Baehr's active career, particularly as president of the Health Insurance Plan, 1950-1957, the extensive correspondence (1941-1975) reflects Baehr's activity in a wide variety of public positions and professional organizations. Included are files for the Public Health Council of New York State, the Mayor's Committee on Medical Care, 1937-1943, and the Health Insurance Plan of Greater New York, 1940-1978. The writings are not complete but include reprints of articles and the text of speeches for 1935-1977. The principal topics are medical economics, medical and hospital care and public health. There is also a small amount of family correspondence and biographical material. Photographic documentation includes albums showing the work of the expedition to the Balkans and Russia of the American Red Cross Typhus Commission (of which Baehr was a member), albums of World War I photographs and scrapbooks relating to his career (1912-1963). These papers form part of the Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection.
Baehr, George, 1887-1978
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Dr. Barbara Baehr, 1978, and Arthur J. Viseltear, 1979.
Existence and Location of Copies
Scrapbooks are available on microfilm (1,008 frames on 1 reel, 35mm.) from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost. Order no. HM123.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series: I. Correspondence and Subject Files. II. Writings. III. Personal Papers.
Scope and Contents
The Baehr Papers consist of seven linear feet of correspondence and subject files, writings, scrapbooks, and photograph albums. The papers are very fragmented and often routine, and provide limited coverage of Baehr's career-long involvement with the Health Insurance Plan of Greater New York, Inc. There is almost no material from Baehr's term as president and medical director of H.I.P. and what information there is concerns the establishment of H.I.P. rather than the administration of the organization. The papers do, however, include some information on the Mayor's Committee on Medical Care, selected items regarding the founding and operations of H.I.P., and a few general correspondence files from 1941 forward. The scrapbooks and photograph albums cover Baehr's service during World Wars I and II and also include personal and family photographs and other materials. The papers are organized in three series: CORRESPONDENCE AND SUBJECT FILES, WRITINGS, and PERSONAL PAPERS.
Series I, CORRESPONDENCE AND SUBJECT FILES, is organized in three sections: General, Mayor's Committee on Medical Care, and Health Insurance Plan of Greater New York, Inc. The General files are arranged alphabetically and span the years 1941 to 1975. The files include correspondence, circulars, announcements, mimeographed reports, and other material. The two folders for the United States Office of Civilian Defense contain memoranda regarding Baehr's travels in the United States during 1941-1944, a diary from a 1942 trip to England, and statistics on shortages in medical personnel. The files for several organizations in which Baehr was active including the Public Health Council of New York State, the Committee for National Health Insurance, and the State Communities Aid Association, contain material regarding fluoridation of water supplies, national health insurance, and other medical and public health issues. The other files in the section date primarily from the period after Baehr retired from H.I.P. The material, though frequently routine in nature, reflects Baehr's involvement in a wide variety of professional and civic organizations and his contacts and interaction with public officials and leaders in public health and medicine.
The Mayor's Committee on Medical Care section consists of eight folders of correspondence, memoranda, minutes, draft reports, and print material from the Subcommittee on Plan and Scope.
The Health Insurance Plan of Greater New York section extends from 1940 to 1978 but is fragmentary. The early material includes information on the Vladeck Houses program and on the founding of H.I.P.; folder 103 contains several historical sketches of the plan.
Series II, WRITINGS, is arranged chronologically and consists of approximately eighty reprints and fifty mimeographed speech texts spanning the years 1935 to 1977. It also includes a draft bibliography prepared by Baehr, circa 1970, and miscellaneous programs and letters.
The series represents only a portion of Baehr's total writings. The principal topics represented are medical economics, medical and hospital care, and public health. Fifteen reprints and speech texts directly concern H.I.P., and several others use the plan as an example to illustrate trends in health care. With the exception of several articles on Lupus Erythematosus, mostly from the 1940s, the series contains almost none of Baehr's medical research papers.
Series III, PERSONAL PAPERS, is organized in three sections: General, Photographs, and Scrapbooks. The first section extends from 1917 to 1978 and is arranged chronologically. It includes correspondence concerning family personal business, curriculum vitae, certificates and honors, newsclippings, and a variety of biographical material. The transcript and audio recording of "An Evening with George Baehr," American Public Health Association, Medical Care Section annual meeting (1965 Oct), is of special interest. The section also includes the transcript of an oral history interview with Baehr conducted by the Columbia University Oral History Research Office.
The Photographs section includes two albums, one from Baehr's service with the American Red Cross Typhus Commission and the other from his service as commander of an army base hospital in France, which provide interesting documentation of public health and medical conditions in two areas of Europe during World War I. Other material in the section includes personal and family photographs from 1942 to 1977.
Scrapbooks consists of five books of correspondence, photographs, personal items such as medals, awards, and certificates, and a variety of memorabilia. The section also contains two bound volumes received by Baehr at a testimonial dinner in 1957. The material in the five scrapbooks was removed and microfilmed in 1981. These filmed scrapbooks contained a large quantity of deteriorating newsprint which was discarded after filming. The remaining material was foldered and is included in the section.
The five filmed scrapbooks (See: MICROFILM HM 123) each focus on a specific period or topic, although each contains a few items unrelated to the topic. The books are described below in the order in which they appear on the film:
Book 1 (1912-1913, 1933-1941), Baehr's European trip of 1912-1913, where he conducted postdoctoral research in the Universities of Freiburg and Vienna: miscellaneous items from the 1930s. Microfilm frames 1-91.
Book 2 (1941-1947), Baehr's tenure as chief medical officer of the Office of Civilian Defense, including the trip to the Mexican "Primer Curso Regional Administration de Hospitales" which Baehr undertook as O.C.D. representative; miscellaneous items. Microfilm frames 92-508.
Book 3 (1942) 1947-1949), Baehr's chairmanship of the American Public Health Association's Lasker Award Committee; miscellaneous items. Microfilm frames 509-681.
Book 4 (1943-1954, 1963), Baehr's presidency and medical directorship of the Health Insurance Plan of Greater New York, Inc. (H.I.P.); miscellaneous items. Microfilm frames 682-847.
Book 5 (1950-1951, 1959-1962), further material relating to H.I.P. and the Lasker Award Committee, as well as miscellany. Microfilm frames 848-908.
The Baehr Papers were presented to Yale University Library by Dr. Baehr's daughter, Dr. Barbara Baehr, in 1978. The Baehr Papers are part of the Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection.
Biographical / Historical
George Baehr (1887-1978), in his seventy-year career as a medical educator, clinician, and group health prepayment plan founder and administrator, bridged the fields of medical care and clinical medicine. Born in New York City, Baehr completed the required one year of undergraduate work at Columbia College in 1904 and entered the Columbia College of Physicians and Surgeons, where he received the M.D. degree in 1908. After completing an internship and residency in surgery at Mount Sinai Hospital, New York City, he studied pathology, physiology, and biochemistry at the Universities of Freiburg and Vienna from 1911 to 1913. Baehr returned to Mount Sinai in 1913, where he held a succession of appointments and served as attending physician, director of medicine, and director of clinical research from 1927 to 1950. While at Mount Sinai his research contributions covered a wide area and included work in collagen diseases, renal complications of heart disease, and hematology. He was also a pioneer in the field of continuing medical education.
Baehr became involved in public health during World War I, as a member of the American Red Cross Typhus Fever Commission to the Balkans and the Ukraine in 1915-1916. After America's entry in the war, he served as commander of an army base hospital in France from 1918 to 1919.
In 1931 Baehr established an early experiment in prepaid medical care at Mount Sinai, establishing the Consultation Service for People of Moderate Means which provided medical services for a flat fee. Following the election of his long-time friend, Fiorello LaGuardia, as reform mayor of New York in 1933, Baehr acted as mayoral advisor on health and social planning and served on a number of boards. In 1939 LaGuardia and Baehr established an innovative health care program for residents of the Vladeck Houses, the first low-income city/state housing. By opting to add one dollar to their monthly rent, residents could receive physician care for their families in their homes.
On LaGuardia's recommendation Baehr was appointed Chief Medical Officer for National Civilian Defense in 1941, and on his travels throughout the country Baehr was able to study existing group practice and prepayment plans. Baehr brought this knowledge, in 1943, to LaGuardia's Mayor's Committee on Medical Care. which had been created to develop a health services program for the city. When the committee was unable to reach a consensus among three proposed health delivery systems: compulsory health insurance, prepaid group practice, or a fee-for-service indemnity plan with limited benefit coverage, LaGuardia opted for the prepaid group practice which Baehr espoused. Baehr was then appointed chairman of the Subcommittee on Plan and Scope.
This subcommittee outlined a group practice prepayment plan which, four years later, provided the basis for the Health Insurance Plan of Greater New York, Inc. (H.I.P.). In 1945, as physicians were released from military service, Baehr and Dr. Dean Clark began recruiting them for medical group practices in the city, and with support from several foundations, Baehr and others succeeded in establishing in 1947 the Health Insurance Plan of Greater New York, Inc.
Baehr served as president and medical director of H.I.P. from 1950 to 1957, during which time the plan struggled successfully, against opposition from organized medicine, to expand its program and to become one of the largest and most effective prepayment group practice plans in the country. Following his retirement in 1957, Baehr continued to serve H.I.P. as a special medical consultant.
In addition to his professional appointments and service as an advisor to Mayor LaGuardia, Baehr participated in a variety of state and national medical and public health societies, was a member of the New York State Public Health Council from 1933 to 1975 (chairman 1955-1969), and was recognized nationally as an influential spokesman for reform of health care delivery systems.
Hospital care; Medical care; Medical economics; Medicine; National health services; Public health; World War, 1914-1918 -- Medical care; Physicians; Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection; Baehr, George, 1887-1978; Esselstyn, Caldwell B., 1902-1975; Harriman, W. Averell (William Averell), 1891-1986; Javits, Jacob K. (Jacob Koppel), 1904-1986; Kennedy, Edward M. (Edward Moore), 1932-2009; La Guardia, Fiorello H. (Fiorello Henry), 1882-1947; Lindsay, John V. (John Vliet), 1921-2000; Lombardi, Tarky; New York (N.Y.). Department of Health; New York (N.Y.). Mayor's Committee on Medical Care; New York (State). Department of Health; Public Health Council (N.Y.); Committee for National Health Insurance (U.S.); Health Insurance Plan of Greater New York; New York State Health Planning Commission; New York University. Medical Department; United States. Office of Civilian Defense
- CORRESPONDENCE AND SUBJECT FILES, 1940-1978; Series I; 3 linear feet (6 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  CORRESPONDENCE AND SUBJECT FILES is organized in three sections: General, Mayor's Committee on Medical Care, and Health Insurance Plan of Greater New York, Inc. Files designated with an asterisk contain ten or more items.
  - General
    - A (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Aging, 1955-1957 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - American Friends of Yugoslavia, Inc., 1964, 1973-1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - American Public Health Association, 1945-1971 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Anderson, Warren M., 1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Associated Hospital Service, 1963, 1967-1971 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - B (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Boudreau, Frank G., 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Biggs (Hermann M.) Memorial Award, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Brindle, James, 1965, 1971, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      General
      See also: box 5, folders 95-114
    - Brown, Gordon E., 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      See also: box 4, folder 75
    - C (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Carey, Hugh L., 1974-1977 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Commission on the Delivery of Personal Health Services (New York City), 1967-1970 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Committee for National Health Insurance (*), 1968-1977 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Committee for National Health Insurance, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Committee on Health
      See: box 1, folder 17
    - Community Service Society (New York City), 1973-1976 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Conference on Financing Health Care for the Aged
      See: box 1, folder 2
    - Consumer Commission on the Accreditation of Health Services, 1972-1975 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - D (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Davis, Michael M., 1965, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Deardorff, Neva R.
      See: box 3, folder 57
    - Dearing, W. Palmer, 1961, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - E (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Esselstyn, Caldwell B., 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Esselstyn (Caldwell B.) Memorial Fund
      See: box 2, folder 22
    - F (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Fine, Max
      See: box 1, folders 15-16
    - G (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Gluckman, Edward T.
      See: box 2, folder 18
    - Governor's Conference on the Problems of the Aging
    - Gregg, Alan, 1944, 1952-1956 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Group Health Association of America, 1966, 1970, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - H (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Harriman, W. Averill, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Health and Hospital Planning Council of Southern New York, Inc., 1972-1974, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Hilleboe, Herman E., 1963, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - HMO International of California, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Hospitals, 1963, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - International Committee for the Preparation of the Sixth Decennial Revision of the International Lists of Diseases and Causes of Death
      See: box 4, folder 78
    - J (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Javits, Jacob K., 1975-1977 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - K - L (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Kennedy, Edward M., 1971 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - LaGuardia, Fiorello H.
      See: box 5, folders 87-114
    - LaGuardia Hospital, 1969-1971, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - LaGuardia, Marie (Mrs. Fiorello H.), 1969-1971 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - LaGuardia Memorial Association, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Lewisohn Experiment, 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 38)
      See also: box 2, folder 44
    - Lewisohn, Richard
      See: box 2, folder 38
    - Libman (Emanuel) Memorial Fund, 1946-1956 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Lindsay, John V., 1966, 1971-1973 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Lombardi, Tarky (*), 1972-1975 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - M (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Mayor's Task Force on Reorganization of New York City Government, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Medical care, 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 44)
      See also: box 4, folders 82-83
    - Medical Committee for Human Rights, 1967-1969 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Medical Society of the County of New York, 1950-1952, 1965, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Metcalf, George R.
      See: box 3, folder 61
    - Mount Sinai School of Medicine of the City University of New York, 1964-1966, 1968-1977 (Box 3, Folder 47-48)
    - National Citizens Committee for the World Health Organization, 1954-1957, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Nelbach, Philip E.
      See: box 1, folder 3
    - New York Academy of Medicine, 1942-1948, 1954-1977 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - New York Academy of Sciences, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - New York City Bicentennial Corporation, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - New York City Department of Health, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - New York City Department of Hospitals, 1950-1951 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - New York City Department of Hospitals, 1964-1972, undated (Box 3, Folder 55)
      See also: box 1, folder 14
    - New York City Health and Hospital Corporation, 1970-1973 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - New York City Welfare Council, 1944, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - New York Committee on Workmen's Compensation, undated (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - New York Labor-Management Council of Health and Welfare Plans, Inc., 1963-1965 (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - New York State Committee for National Health Security, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - New York State Department of Health, 1950-1967, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - New York State Department of Health, Public Health Council, 1955-1974 (Box 3, Folder 62-64)
    - New York State Department of Health, Public Health Council, 1975, undated (Box 4, Folder 65)
      See also: box 1, folder 13
    - New York State Health Planning Commission, 1967-1968 (Box 4, Folder 66)
    - New York State Report from the Governor's Steering Committee on Social Problems of Health Services and Costs, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 67)
    - Noguchi, Hideyo, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 68)
    - North Rockland Health Center
      See: box 3, folders 64-65
    - O - P (Box 4, Folder 69)
    - Parran, Thomas, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 70)
      See also: box 4, folder 81
    - Peckham Experiment, 1943-1948 (Box 4, Folder 71)
    - R (Box 4, Folder 72)
    - Rubin, Donald
    - S - T (Box 4, Folder 73)
    - Sedgwick Memorial Award
      See: box 8, folder 11
    - Society of Medical Administrators, 1967-1971 (Box 4, Folder 74)
    - State Charities Aid Association
      See: box 4, folder 76
    - State Communities Aid Association (*), 1943, 1966-1974 (Box 4, Folder 75)
    - State Communities Aid Association, 1975-1978 (Box 4, Folder 76)
    - U (Box 4, Folder 77)
    - United States Committee on Joint Causes of Death, 1945-1949 (Box 4, Folder 78)
    - United States Department of Health, Education and Welfare, 1967-1968, 1974-1975 (Box 4, Folder 79)
    - United States Executive Office of the President, President's Commission on the Health Needs of the Nation, 1952-1954 (Box 4, Folder 80)
    - United States Federal Security Agency, Public Health Service, 1941-1950, undated (Box 4, Folder 81)
    - United States Office of Civilian Defense (*), 1941-1950 (Box 4, Folder 82-83)
    - W - Y (Box 4, Folder 84)
    - West Indies, University of, 1964-1966 (Box 4, Folder 85)
    - Unidentified correspondence, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 86)
  - Mayor's Committee on Medical Care
    - Printed material re: Plan and Scope Sub-committee, 1937-1943 (Box 5, Folder 87)
    - Member lists and committee requirement re: Plan and Scope Sub-committee, 1943 Apr, undated (Box 5, Folder 88)
    - Correspondence and memoranda re: Plan and Scope Sub-committee, 1943 May-July (Box 5, Folder 89)
    - Minutes re: Medical Services Sub-committee, 1943 June 7 (Box 5, Folder 90)
    - Agendas and minutes re: Plan and Scope Sub-committee, 1943 June-November (Box 5, Folder 91)
    - Correspondence and memoranda re: Plan and Scope Sub-committee, 1943 September-December (Box 5, Folder 92)
    - Reports re: Plan and Scope Sub-committee, 1943 October 1, undated (Box 5, Folder 93)
    - Health insurance plan drafts, outlines and related material re: Plan and Scope Sub-committee, 1943 October-Dec, undated (Box 5, Folder 94)
  - Health Insurance Plan of Greater New York
    - Outline, plan and report re: Vladeck Houses, 1940, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 95)
    - Prospectus re: founding, 1944 (Box 5, Folder 96)
    - Correspondence re: founding, 1944-1945 (Box 5, Folder 97)
    - Memoranda and reports re: founding, 1944-1945 (Box 5, Folder 98)
    - Newsclippings re: founding, 1944-1945 (Box 5, Folder 99)
    - Summary proposals, notes and related material re: founding, 1944-1946 (Box 5, Folder 100)
    - Annual and statistical reports, 1952, 1960-1961, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 101)
    - Newsletters, 1954, 1961, undated (Box 6, Folder 102)
    - Historical reports, 1954-1956, 1970-1978 (Box 6, Folder 103)
    - Memoranda and related material, 1961-1962 (Box 6, Folder 104)
    - Correspondence, memoranda and related material, 1962-1963, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 105)
    - Certificate of Incorporation and bylaws, 1962-1969, 1973, undated (Box 6, Folder 106)
    - Correspondence, memoranda and related material, 1971 May-1973 (Box 6, Folder 107-110)
    - Correspondence and memoranda re: Medical Control Board, 1973-1975 (Box 6, Folder 111)
    - Correspondence and memoranda, 1974-1978 (Box 6, Folder 112-113)
    - Memoranda, report and outline, undated (Box 6, Folder 114)
      See also: box 1, folder 6
- WRITINGS, 1935-1978; Series II; 0.25; (1 box)
  WRITINGS is arranged chronologically.
  - Bibliography, Circa 1970 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Writings, 1935-1964 (Box 7, Folder 2-11)
  - Correspondence re: Michael M. Davis lecture, 1965 July-August (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Writings, 1965-1978, undated (Box 7, Folder 13-15)
- PERSONAL PAPERS, 1915-1978; Series III; 2 linear feet (5 boxes)
  PERSONAL PAPERS is organized in three sections: General, Photographs, and Scrapbooks. Each section is arranged chronologically.
  - General material
    - Passport books, vaccination register and war ration books, 1917, 1938, 1948, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Memoranda re: World War I, 1917-1919 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence: Francine Baehr, 1918-1941 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Citations, honors, certificates and outline, 1919-1952 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence re: appointments, 1939, 1965-1967 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Newsclippings, 1941-1977, undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence: Francine Baehr, 1942-1954 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Curriculum vitae, 1943, 1950-1977 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence re: grandchildren, 1964, 1966 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Audio recording and transcript, "An Evening with George Baehr,", 1965 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Citations, honors and certificates, 1967-1977 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Biographical sketches, 1971, 1977-1978 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence: family and business, 1972-1977 (Box 8, Folder 13)